<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Extroverted Introspection]]></title>
  <link href="http://milgner.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://milgner.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-01T15:23:14+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://milgner.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Marcus Ilgner]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[blog@marcusilgner.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[StoryMOOC and Star Wars]]></title>
    <link href="http://milgner.github.io/blog/2013/10/28/storymooc-and-star-wars/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-28T20:25:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://milgner.github.io/blog/2013/10/28/storymooc-and-star-wars</id>
    
      











      <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http%3A%2F%2Fmilgner.github.io%2Fblog%2F2013%2F10%2F28%2Fstorymooc-and-star-wars%2F&amp;user_id=ma_il&amp;title=StoryMOOC+and+Star+Wars&amp;category=text&amp;description=Writing+about+things+I+learn%2C+think+and+do.+Topics+may+involve+software+development%2C+psychology+and+music.&amp;tags=storymooc" type="text/html" />
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This weeks post has to do with the course <a href="https://iversity.org/c/6?r=5ced0">&ldquo;The Future of Storytelling&rdquo;</a>
which recently started on the new platform <a href="https://iversity.org?r=5ced0">Iversity</a>.</p>

<p>I have been interested in this subject for some time now, especially in
collaborative storytelling in role-playing games, so when this course came along,
I knew I couldn&rsquo;t miss it.</p>

<p>What makes this course a bit different from the other courses I took in the past,
is that it seems to involve actual writing and storytelling. At the end of each
week (a &ldquo;chapter&rdquo;) the students are given a task which to accomplish.</p>

<p>The task for this week, to be executed in this very blog post for your reading pleasure:</p>

<blockquote><p>Please think about which story you have read, seen, listened to, played or experienced has impressed you most in your life. … Which story can you still very well remember? Write down both, the summary of this story (what you remember of the story, not what Wikipedia says.. :) and – on the other hand: – what made it so special to you that you can still remember it.</p></blockquote>

<p>So here is the story how <em>Star Wars</em> changed my life:</p>

<h3>The Hero&rsquo;s Journey</h3>

<p>A regular summary of the <em>Star Wars</em> story is probably quite uninteresting for
everyone who hasn&rsquo;t been living under a rock the last 30 years. From a storytelling
point of view, it is quite unremarkable, even: a science-fiction-themed fairytale
describing the classical <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monomyth">&ldquo;hero&rsquo;s journey&rdquo;</a>
as described by Joseph Campbell in &ldquo;The Hero with a Thousand Faces&rdquo;.
I use the term &ldquo;fairytale&rdquo; because it has many resemblances to traditional folk
tales: from the way it starts off with the sentence &ldquo;A long time ago&hellip;&rdquo; to the
distinctive way that characters are painted good or evil and employing easily-
recognizable archetypes.</p>

<h4>Yodas wisdom</h4>

<p>I don&rsquo;t remember exactly how old I was when I watched the first <em>Star Wars</em> movies,
but I guess I must have been around 10 years.
The scene that would have such a lasting effect on my life is from the beginning
of &ldquo;The Empire Strikes Back&rdquo;, the second movie of the <em>Star Wars</em> trilogy.
The alien Yoda, portraied to possess unassailable wisdom, is mentoring Luke, the
protagonist and training him to use the <em>Force</em>.
When Luke struggles with a particular mental excercise, Yoda utters this quote:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Fear is the path to the dark side: Fear leads to anger, Anger leads to hate, Hate leads to Suffering&rdquo;.</p></blockquote>

<p>I could not help but ponder this quote, comparing it to my own observations and
found much merit in it.
My 9th birthday, 17th January 1991 had coincided with the starting date of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation_Desert_Storm">Operation Desert Storm</a>.
My parents television was running and I still remember the pictures of war, slowly
coming to a first understanding of the situation in the world and wondering how
it could have come this. Why people were building were expending all this energy
to build high-tech jets and other weaponry just to kill each other.</p>

<h4>Becoming a <del>Jedi</del> Zen Master</h4>

<p>The <em>Star Wars</em> movie awakened in me the notion that people are driven to this
behaviour via these emotions, fear and anger, followed by hate.
The story also told how engaging in evil acts &ndash; those associated with the <em>Dark
Side</em> &ndash; would have a poisonous effect on someones character, leading them down a
road towards more and more evil.
And since it was clear to my young and impressionable mind that I didn&rsquo;t want to
be evil, I concluded that I would ever need to be wary of these emotions, fear,
anger and hate and where they could lead me.
In this aspect, <em>Star Wars</em> fulfilled another aspect rooted in the origins of
storytelling: providing examples for socially desirable behaviour, worthy of imitation.</p>

<p>Understand that I didn&rsquo;t want to become a <em>Jedi Knight</em> or somesuch thing: I fully
realized the fictional aspect of what I had seen. Nonetheless, &ldquo;Don&rsquo;t fall to the
<em>Dark Side</em>&rdquo; became some kind of a motto for me.
And I can say that I have successfully managed to adhere to my old tenets until
today. So much even, that a few years back a friend of mine jokingly called me
&ldquo;Zen Master Marcus&rdquo;. It was just a stray remark but I still find it hilarious.</p>

<p>And surely enough: to this day I have read enough books and listened to enough
Psychology lectures to have garnered a much more differentiated understanding of
emotions and the way to the &ldquo;<em>Dark Side</em>&rdquo;.
But I also have experienced people acting cruel and callous. Both in reaction to
being hurt and out of desire for power and control over others when they themselves
seemed to lack control of their own lifes.
This makes me think that the simple Yoda version works well enough as an
approximation to the truths behind the self-perpetuating suffering. And it&rsquo;s
certainly easier than trying to explain social psychology studies to a ten-year-old.</p>

<h4>Bonus part</h4>

<p>So much for the #StoryMOOC task. But funnily enough there is a second aspect on
how <em>Star Wars</em> influenced my life. It probably could have been any other movie,
too, so this is kind of a bonus scene in this blog post.</p>

<p>At the age of 13 or 14 years I started having occasional nightmares. Therein I
was chased by evil characters who wanted to shoot me. After a few repetitions &ndash;
each one some time apart: this is not that kind of story where the young boy is
haunted by nightmares every night &ndash; the pursuers turned from gangsters shooting
at me into the droids C-3PO and R2-D2 from the <em>Star Wars</em> movie.
Ok, now I should probably give you some time to stop laughing. Awake, I found the
notion quite ridiculous myself: the meanest thing C-3PO would have been able to
do was to call you a <em>buffoon</em> in 6 million forms of communication.
Sure, R2-D2 could probably use his 1337 hacking skillz to crack your social media
profiles and post &ldquo;My mother can&rsquo;t cook.&rdquo; to your wall, but back then there wasn&rsquo;t
even an internet.</p>

<p>Nonetheless, these two robots were in my dreams, chasing me through the village
and into my room upstairs. How R2-D2 managed to climb the stairs in my parents&#8217;
house, I&rsquo;ll never know.
But the same dream continued to occur. And since it was always the same dream,
after a few months I started to recognize it as such. And once I figured out I
was in a dream, I decided that I should just jump out of the window: to die and
thus wake from the dream.
The first time I did this I was more scared of trying this than from the actual
nightmare. But it worked and I could wake, turn around in my bed and fall peacefully
asleep again.
The second time &ndash; or maybe third, I don&rsquo;t exactly remember &ndash; I grew more adventurous.
Since it was a dream, I decided, I didn&rsquo;t need to die but I could as well fly away
from the two figures who, even though relentless as robots, were quite slow and could
never catch me. And once again it worked. Unbeknown to my younger self, I had taken
my first steps &ndash; or flight &ndash; in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucid_dream">Lucid dreaming</a>.
All combined, I can say without doubt that <em>Star Wars</em> spiked both my desire in mastering
my emotions and realizing that, with some training, I could master my consciousness
enough to even control my dreams.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[For a short break - I wish]]></title>
    <link href="http://milgner.github.io/blog/2013/10/15/for-a-short-break-i-wish/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-15T22:37:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://milgner.github.io/blog/2013/10/15/for-a-short-break-i-wish</id>
    
      











      <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http%3A%2F%2Fmilgner.github.io%2Fblog%2F2013%2F10%2F15%2Ffor-a-short-break-i-wish%2F&amp;user_id=ma_il&amp;title=For+a+short+break+-+I+wish&amp;category=text&amp;description=Writing+about+things+I+learn%2C+think+and+do.+Topics+may+involve+software+development%2C+psychology+and+music.&amp;tags=" type="text/html" />
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Now for a short break. Or make that a wish for more breaks. Time has been
especially short for me for the last few weeks. I even had to cancel my vacation
&ndash; just when I was looking forward to catching up on my MOOCs.</p>

<p>But all crunchtime must come to an end and there really are some interesting
courses to look forward to, too.</p>

<p>Although I&rsquo;m hopelessly behind schedule on &ldquo;Think Again&rdquo;, I&rsquo;ll also pick up
that one again. I must admit that week 3 found me  in a kind of unmotivated mood
as the course was progressing quite slowly and the application of the subject
matter eluded me.
The topic for week 4 is Propositional Logic and Truth Tables: quite familiar
ground for people with an IT background, so I&rsquo;ll probably be able to breeze
through that part.
After that the topic seems to become more complex and I also feel like I can see
an arch emerging that goes from analyzing arguments to developing ones own
arguments.
But even if I&rsquo;ll probably not be able to apply the topic at hand in the way I
originally presumed, I guess I still may find it highly useful for my personal
contemplations.</p>

<p>And as if my list of interesting MOOCs wasn&rsquo;t long enough already, a new MOOC
portal, <a href="https://iversity.org">Iversity</a> opened its doors just today.
Among the initial course lineup there&rsquo;s one I find especially interesting:
<a href="https://iversity.org/c/6?r=5ced0">The Future Of Storytelling</a>.
Ever since first playing a round of the <a href="http://www.bullypulpitgames.com/games/fiasco/">Fiasco roleplaying game</a>
a couple of months ago, I found myself more and more intrigued with the topic of
Storytelling.
I also watched the first week of <a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/onlinegames">Online Games: Literature, New Media, and Narrative</a> on Coursera, but somehow couldn&rsquo;t really warm to it.
So I&rsquo;m really looking forward to this course on Iversity.
The hashtag is #storymooc &ndash; see you there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA["Think Again", Weeks 1+2]]></title>
    <link href="http://milgner.github.io/blog/2013/09/05/think-again/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-05T00:03:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://milgner.github.io/blog/2013/09/05/think-again</id>
    
      











      <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http%3A%2F%2Fmilgner.github.io%2Fblog%2F2013%2F09%2F05%2Fthink-again%2F&amp;user_id=ma_il&amp;title=%22Think+Again%22%2C+Weeks+1%2B2&amp;category=text&amp;description=Writing+about+things+I+learn%2C+think+and+do.+Topics+may+involve+software+development%2C+psychology+and+music.&amp;tags=coursera" type="text/html" />
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I started <a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/thinkagain">Think Again: How to Reason and Argue</a>
with a mix of curiosity and genuine interest. In the past, I have often come across
bad reasoning and although I learned to identify some items from the <a href="http://www.nizkor.org/features/fallacies/index.html">long list of fallacies</a>,
I am not confident that I can formulate my own arguments in a well-structured way
when in spontaneous situations.</p>

<p>Also, I&rsquo;m currently reading <a href="http://www.amazon.de/Thinking-Fast-and-Slow-ebook/dp/B00555X8OA?tag=aflattrcom997-21">Thinking, Fast and Slow</a>
and I felt like attending &ldquo;Think Again&rdquo; might work well in conjuction, even though
they are about different subjects: the latter is about psychology in general while
this course is about arguments and reasoning.</p>

<p>However, after just finishing the video lectures and excercises for the second week,
I&rsquo;m positively surprised by how well-made and entertaining it is.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>As usual, the lectures in the first week were very basic: defining the subject of
the course (&ldquo;What is an Argument?&rdquo;) and giving a bit of background information
on what arguments are used for: justification and explanation.
Personally I found the last part to be the most interesting: the differentiation
between linguistic acts, speech acts and conversational acts.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not sure how it will tie into the rest of the course but I certainly enjoyed
the corresponding lectures. Especially the mention of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buffalo_buffalo_Buffalo_buffalo_buffalo_buffalo_Buffalo_buffalo">Buffalo buffalo Buffalo</a>
totally cracked me up. It&rsquo;s a great example how one can perform a linguistic act
(i.e. stringing together a couple of words into a meaningful sentence) without
it being conversational since it cannot actually be understood by the audience.
This so far seems to be a recurring motive in the lectures: words and sentences
can take on completely different meaning and function, depending on where and how
they are used.</p>

<p>Also, the introduction to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cooperative_principle">Gricean maxims</a>
was very interesting. Wikipedia cites some criticism of the concept but it is my
personal conviction that, of course, communication should be intended to be
constructive and cooperative, so following these maxims would be a good idea.</p>

<p>Back to the course itself, the second week become more hands on. After introducing
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logical_form">argument standard form</a>, a number of
argument markers and elements were presented, followed by about 40 minutes of
applying these using a newspaper article.
What struck me as somewhat strange was the part about avoiding the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skeptical_regress">skeptical regress</a>.
While it is obvious that one doesn&rsquo;t want to needlessly challenge every premise,
I stumbled over the bit where the professor mentioned that assuring your audience
using authority can be a good thing. Even or &ndash; due to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confirmation_bias">confirmation bias</a>
and other psychological phenomena &ndash; <em>especially</em> someone very familiar with a given
topic can be prone to erroneous judgement.
So I missed some kind of interjection that, given evidence for doubt, one should
always follow up on skeptical objections to premises. Just countering with a
reference to authority cannot be the solution.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, the course so far is highly entertaining and very interesting. It&rsquo;s
still possible to join in, but in case you currently don&rsquo;t have the time or are
still unsure, whether it&rsquo;s for you, make sure to follow the blog for updates in
the coming weeks.</p>

<p>At the moment, there are 126.000 students attending the course. Let&rsquo;s see how
many will stay with it. For the moment, I definitely want to.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Starting out - a mission statement]]></title>
    <link href="http://milgner.github.io/blog/2013/09/01/starting-out/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-01T13:03:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://milgner.github.io/blog/2013/09/01/starting-out</id>
    
      











      <link rel="payment" href="https://flattr.com/submit/auto?url=http%3A%2F%2Fmilgner.github.io%2Fblog%2F2013%2F09%2F01%2Fstarting-out%2F&amp;user_id=ma_il&amp;title=Starting+out+-+a+mission+statement&amp;category=text&amp;description=Writing+about+things+I+learn%2C+think+and+do.+Topics+may+involve+software+development%2C+psychology+and+music.&amp;tags=imho%2C%2Cmeta" type="text/html" />
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So, here I am. To be fair, this is already my third attempt at starting a blog.
The first two tries were quite unsuccessful because I either got tripped up with
superficial issues like layout and typography or didn&rsquo;t have a clear idea about
what I was going to write about.</p>

<p>With probably tens of thousands of blogs on the subjects of software development,
yet another one discussing how to set up Rails 4 on JRuby<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> <em>may</em> be of interest
to a few people, but only for a short time at best. And having a topic that you
can continually write about is the most important thing to avoid being overrun in
digital spiderwebs.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>And so we come to what is going to be one of the important themes on this site:
self-reflection and -improvement.</p>

<ol>
<li>Solution 1: I just set up a simple <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> theme.</li>
<li>Solution 2: The mission statement: writing about all the interesting courses
I take, books I read and sometimes other things that I want to get off my
chest.</li>
</ol>


<p>My list of planned topics so far:</p>

<ol>
<li>&ldquo;Think Again: How to Reason and Argue&rdquo; by Walter Sinnott-Armstrong and Ram Neta on <a href="https://class.coursera.org/thinkagain-002/">Coursera</a>.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.de/Thinking-Fast-and-Slow-ebook/dp/B00555X8OA?tag=aflattrcom997-21">&ldquo;Thinking, Fast and Slow&rdquo;</a> by Daniel Kahneman</li>
<li>&ldquo;Sun Tzu in the office: it&rsquo;s not a battlefield, stupid&rdquo;: inspired by <a href="http://www.inc.com/magazine/20040701/management.html">this post on Inc.com</a></li>
<li>&ldquo;Grundlagen der Sozialpsychologie II&rdquo; by Prof. Dr. Dieter Frey from LMU Munich on <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/de/itunes-u/grundlagen-der-sozialpsychologie/id422005471">iTunes U</a></li>
<li>&ldquo;Rechtsphilosophie&rdquo; by Prof. em. Dr. jur. Dr. jur. h.c. mult. Bernd Schünemann from LMU Munich on <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/de/itunes-u/lmu-rechtsphilosophie/id575246916">iTunes U</a></li>
</ol>


<p>Especially the various Coursera courses I take should provide material for about
one article a week, varying in length. Of course the blog will not in any way be
able to be a substite for actually taking the respective classes. But I hope I&rsquo;ll
be able to give you some insight into what it&rsquo;s all about and so you can decide
whether you want to sign up for one of its future sessions yourself.</p>

<h3>A note about comments</h3>

<p>As you may have noticed, there are no comment forms on the blog. One reason is
that the Disqus platform that&rsquo;s integrated with Octopress has been giving me lots
of headaches in the past.</p>

<p>But the other, much graver reason is that I&rsquo;m completely flabberghasted about the
law regarding comments on webpages in Germany. In a nutshell, it would require
very strict oversight and moderation on my part because if somebody &ndash; in an attempt
to troll, spam or for whatever reason &ndash; posts something that&rsquo;s illegal in Germany,
I would be personally held responsible.
And although I&rsquo;m doing this as a hobby, the fact that posts may occasionally
include software-development-related topics could lead a potential judge to
classify the blog as a &ldquo;commercial&rdquo; blog, leading to even more responsibilities.</p>

<p>But let&rsquo;s make it into an advantage: if you want to share your thoughts on a
certain subject, please <a href="mailto:blog@marcusilgner.com">send me a mail</a> and I will
respond or even make a follow-up post out of it.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m looking forward to getting feedback and hope I&rsquo;ll be able to inspire your own
thinking and learning.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I did that when Rails 4 was still in heavy development and JRuby not officially supported yet. It was fun, including writing some custom <a href="https://gist.github.com/milgner/4410238">PKCS#5 compatibility code</a>.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
