<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Marcus Ilgner</title>
    <link>https://marcusilgner.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Marcus Ilgner</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2019 16:45:35 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://marcusilgner.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://marcusilgner.com/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2019 16:45:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcusilgner.com/projects/</guid>
      <description>Here&amp;rsquo;s a short excerpt from my past and current (public) projects:
 Keedrop: easily &amp;amp; securely send passwords. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t replace GPG, but at least you won&amp;rsquo;t have to send them in plaintext over chat or email. k290-fnkeyctl: when I got myself annoyed with the way that my Logitech keyboard handled its function keys, I reverse-engineered a small application to switch the behaviour on Linux. SQLite3-WinRT, metro-driver and Win8-Cucumber.js: working at doo (nowadays called Scanbot), we pioneered development on the then new Windows 8 platform and wrote a SQLite3 adapter as well as tooling for automated testing of our application.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>https://marcusilgner.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2019 16:19:45 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcusilgner.com/about/</guid>
      <description>Born 1982, I spent my teenage years witnessing and exploring the rise of the internet. Since, I have been able to gather professional experience in a number of technologies: everything from network security and setting up Sendmail-based mail servers 📨, doing computer games development in C++ and DirectX 🎮, via Java business software 💼 up to web applications with Ruby On Rails 💎.
When I&amp;rsquo;m not sitting in front of a computer screen, trying out new technology, you might find me hiking along the Rhine, the alps or other mountains 🗻.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New website &amp; blogging initiative</title>
      <link>https://marcusilgner.com/posts/new-blog-initiative/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2019 15:46:15 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcusilgner.com/posts/new-blog-initiative/</guid>
      <description>So here&amp;rsquo;s my new website 🎉 And I have plans to start blogging more about IT &amp;amp; software development topics again. My days at evopark are coming to an end and in December I&amp;rsquo;ll start my new job at i22 Digitalagentur in Bonn.
Since I&amp;rsquo;ll have some free time on my hands until then - I decided that I should take some time to clear my head instead of jumping head first from one job into the next - I thought that I should use this time of new beginnings and also update my blog and finally write down some of the things that have been going through my mind in the last couple of months.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>