<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Marcus Ilgner</title>
    <link>https://marcusilgner.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Marcus Ilgner</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language><atom:link href="https://marcusilgner.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://marcusilgner.com/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2020 14:13:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcusilgner.com/projects/</guid>
      <description>Here&amp;rsquo;s a short excerpt from my past and current (public) projects:
 SR6 Character Sheet: when our gaming group switched to online play during the COVID-19 pandemic, I built a digital character sheet for Shadowrun 6 Keedrop: easily &amp;amp; securely send passwords. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t replace GPG, but at least you won&amp;rsquo;t have to send them in plaintext over chat or email. k290-fnkeyctl: when I got myself annoyed with the way that my Logitech keyboard handled its function keys, I reverse-engineered a small application to switch the behaviour on Linux.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>https://marcusilgner.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2019 16:19:45 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcusilgner.com/about/</guid>
      <description>Born 1982, I spent my teenage years witnessing and exploring the rise of the internet. Since, I have been able to gather professional experience in a number of technologies: everything from network security and setting up Sendmail-based mail servers 📨, doing computer games development in C++ and DirectX 🎮, via Java business software 💼 up to web applications with Ruby On Rails 💎. Today I work at i22 Digitalagentur, assisting our customers in introducing new technology into their business.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impressum</title>
      <link>https://marcusilgner.com/imprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2019 16:19:45 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcusilgner.com/imprint/</guid>
      <description>Angaben gemäß § 5 TMG; verantwortlich für den Inhalt nach § 55 Abs. 2 RStV:
Marcus Ilgner
Kölner Str. 98
53840 Troisdorf
Kontakt Fax: 02241 1695662
E-Mail: domain@marcusilgner.com
Haftungsausschluss: Haftung für Links Dieses Angebot enthält Links zu externen Webseiten Dritter, auf deren Inhalte ich keinen Einfluss habe. Deshalb kann ich für diese fremden Inhalte auch keine Gewähr übernehmen. Für die Inhalte der verlinkten Seiten ist stets der jeweilige Anbieter oder Betreiber der Seiten verantwortlich.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
