<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Marcus Ilgner</title>
    <link>https://marcusilgner.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Marcus Ilgner</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 21:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://marcusilgner.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Let&#39;s talk about Pet Projects</title>
      <link>https://marcusilgner.com/posts/2022-05-18-pet-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 21:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcusilgner.com/posts/2022-05-18-pet-projects/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s talk about pet projects    In many years reviewing job applications from software developers, one topic has come up as surprisingly controversial time and again: pet projects, i.e. projects that developers work on on their own time. So let&amp;rsquo;s have a look and see what the fuzz is all about.
From the employers perspective    First, let&amp;rsquo;s look at it from the employers perspective. A colleague of mine once succinctly put it like this: &amp;ldquo;You wouldn&amp;rsquo;t expect a slater to tile a roof in their free time, would you?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rails Value Objects</title>
      <link>https://marcusilgner.com/posts/2022-05-04-rails-value-objects/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 01:06:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcusilgner.com/posts/2022-05-04-rails-value-objects/</guid>
      <description>Value Objects in Rails    While writing yesterdays post about the usage of Hash vs class, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help but think of another powerful tool that helps us to build a well-defined model of our problem domain in the programming language of our choice: the value object.
To understand the value of value objects (scnr), let&amp;rsquo;s take an example: 42. &amp;ldquo;What is 42?&amp;rdquo;, you might be tempted to ask - and rightfully so.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Idiomatic Coding: Ruby Hash (&amp; Python Dict)</title>
      <link>https://marcusilgner.com/posts/2022-05-03-idiomatic-coding-ruby-hashes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 08:48:10 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcusilgner.com/posts/2022-05-03-idiomatic-coding-ruby-hashes/</guid>
      <description>Idiomatic Ruby: Hash vs class    It is no secret that I&amp;rsquo;m a big fan of typed languages. To me, an expressive type system really helps to convey the mental model of the application to the developers maintaining the code base.
As such, I am often dismayed when reading code from untyped interpreted languages. Sure, there are classes in Javascript, Ruby and Python. But very often I find that they&amp;rsquo;re eschewed in favour of just bundling a list of attributes together in an untyped Object, Hash or Dict respectively.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://marcusilgner.com/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 08:45:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcusilgner.com/projects/</guid>
      <description>Here&amp;rsquo;s a short excerpt from my past and current (public) projects:
 SR6 Character Sheet: when our gaming group switched to online play during the COVID-19 pandemic, I built a digital character sheet for Shadowrun 6 Keedrop: easily &amp;amp; securely send passwords. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t replace GPG, but at least you won&amp;rsquo;t have to send them in plaintext over chat or email. k290-fnkeyctl: when I got myself annoyed with the way that my Logitech keyboard handled its function keys, I reverse-engineered a small application to switch the behaviour on Linux.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wikis aren&#39;t meant for software documentation</title>
      <link>https://marcusilgner.com/posts/2021-05-20-no-wikis-for-software-documentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 20:39:10 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcusilgner.com/posts/2021-05-20-no-wikis-for-software-documentation/</guid>
      <description>Wikis aren&amp;rsquo;t meant for software documentation     &amp;ldquo;Documentation is a love letter that you write to your future self.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; Damian Conway Although there are many arguments being made to rationalize our laziness and avoid writing proper documentation, there is no doubt in my mind that good software documentation is a great tool to improve the development lifecycle of long-running projects.
If you know your project is going to be scrapped in 2 months time, feel free to stop reading here and enjoy a good book or a walk outside.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Imprint</title>
      <link>https://marcusilgner.com/imprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 14:45:59 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcusilgner.com/imprint/</guid>
      <description>Impressum    Angaben gemäß § 5 TMG; verantwortlich für den Inhalt nach § 55 Abs. 2 RStV:
 Marcus Ilgner Kölner Str. 98 53840 Troisdorf Deutschland  Kontakt    Fax: 02241 1695662
E-Mail: domain@marcusilgner.com
Haftungsausschluss:    Haftung für Links    Dieses Angebot enthält Links zu externen Webseiten Dritter, auf deren Inhalte ich keinen Einfluss habe. Deshalb kann ich für diese fremden Inhalte auch keine Gewähr übernehmen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deploy a Vert.x app with an embedded SPA</title>
      <link>https://marcusilgner.com/posts/2021-04-04-deploy-vertx-with-embedded-spa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 13:31:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcusilgner.com/posts/2021-04-04-deploy-vertx-with-embedded-spa/</guid>
      <description>Deploy a Vert.x application with an embedded SPA    As a developer I have come to enjoy the versatility and power of the Vert.x platform. And although it contains many utilities for server-side rendering, called Vert.x Web, there are situations where you might want to use a single-page application (SPA) instead.
Concrete reasons for and against SPAs are best kept separate from this. One thing, however, that makes SPAs cumbersome for small teams is having to deploy them separately from the API they will talk to, so having a setup that allows for deploying everything in one go.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>https://marcusilgner.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2019 16:19:45 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcusilgner.com/about/</guid>
      <description>Born 1982, I spent my teenage years witnessing and exploring the rise of the internet. Since, I have been able to gather professional experience in a number of technologies: everything from network security and setting up Sendmail-based mail servers 📨, doing computer games development in C++ and DirectX 🎮, via Java business software 💼 up to web applications with Ruby On Rails 💎 and real-time data processing applications with Vert.x ✈️.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
