<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Marcus Ilgner</title>
    <link>https://marcusilgner.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Marcus Ilgner</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 13:31:04 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://marcusilgner.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Imprint</title>
      <link>https://marcusilgner.com/imprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 14:45:59 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcusilgner.com/imprint/</guid>
      <description>Impressum    Angaben gemäß § 5 TMG; verantwortlich für den Inhalt nach § 55 Abs. 2 RStV:
 Marcus Ilgner Kölner Str. 98 53840 Troisdorf Deutschland  Kontakt    Fax: 02241 1695662
E-Mail: domain@marcusilgner.com
Haftungsausschluss:    Haftung für Links    Dieses Angebot enthält Links zu externen Webseiten Dritter, auf deren Inhalte ich keinen Einfluss habe. Deshalb kann ich für diese fremden Inhalte auch keine Gewähr übernehmen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deploy a Vert.x app with an embedded SPA</title>
      <link>https://marcusilgner.com/posts/2021-04-04-deploy-vertx-with-embedded-spa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 13:31:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcusilgner.com/posts/2021-04-04-deploy-vertx-with-embedded-spa/</guid>
      <description>Deploy a Vert.x application with an embedded SPA    As a developer I have come to enjoy the versatility and power of the Vert.x platform. And although it contains many utilities for server-side rendering, called Vert.x Web, there are situations where you might want to use a single-page application (SPA) instead.
Concrete reasons for and against SPAs are best kept separate from this. One thing, however, that makes SPAs cumbersome for small teams is having to deploy them separately from the API they will talk to, so having a setup that allows for deploying everything in one go.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://marcusilgner.com/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2020 14:13:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcusilgner.com/projects/</guid>
      <description>Here&amp;rsquo;s a short excerpt from my past and current (public) projects:
 SR6 Character Sheet: when our gaming group switched to online play during the COVID-19 pandemic, I built a digital character sheet for Shadowrun 6 Keedrop: easily &amp;amp; securely send passwords. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t replace GPG, but at least you won&amp;rsquo;t have to send them in plaintext over chat or email. k290-fnkeyctl: when I got myself annoyed with the way that my Logitech keyboard handled its function keys, I reverse-engineered a small application to switch the behaviour on Linux.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>https://marcusilgner.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2019 16:19:45 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://marcusilgner.com/about/</guid>
      <description>Born 1982, I spent my teenage years witnessing and exploring the rise of the internet. Since, I have been able to gather professional experience in a number of technologies: everything from network security and setting up Sendmail-based mail servers 📨, doing computer games development in C++ and DirectX 🎮, via Java business software 💼 up to web applications with Ruby On Rails 💎 and real-time data processing applications with Vert.x ✈️.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
