<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: imho, | Extroverted Introspection]]></title>
  <link href="http://milgner.github.io/blog/categories/imho/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://milgner.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-01T17:02:31+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://milgner.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Marcus Ilgner]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[blog@marcusilgner.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Starting out - a mission statement]]></title>
    <link href="http://milgner.github.io/blog/2013/09/01/starting-out/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-01T13:03:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://milgner.github.io/blog/2013/09/01/starting-out</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So, here I am. To be fair, this is already my third attempt at starting a blog.
The first two tries were quite unsuccessful because I either got tripped up with
superficial issues like layout and typography or didn&rsquo;t have a clear idea about
what I was going to write about.</p>

<p>With probably tens of thousands of blogs on the subjects of software development,
yet another one discussing how to set up Rails 4 on JRuby<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> <em>may</em> be of interest
to a few people, but only for a short time at best. And having a topic that you
can continually write about is the most important thing to avoid being overrun in
digital spiderwebs.</p>

<p>And so we come to what is going to be one of the important themes on this site:
self-reflection and -improvement.</p>

<ol>
<li>Solution 1: I just set up a simple <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> theme.</li>
<li>Solution 2: The mission statement: writing about all the interesting courses
I take, books I read and sometimes other things that I want to get off my
chest.</li>
</ol>


<p>My list of planned topics so far:</p>

<ol>
<li>&ldquo;Think Again: How to Reason and Argue&rdquo; by Walter Sinnott-Armstrong and Ram Neta on <a href="https://class.coursera.org/thinkagain-002/">Coursera</a>.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.de/Thinking-Fast-and-Slow-ebook/dp/B00555X8OA?tag=aflattrcom997-21">&ldquo;Thinking, Fast and Slow&rdquo;</a> by Daniel Kahneman</li>
<li>&ldquo;Sun Tzu in the office: it&rsquo;s not a battlefield, stupid&rdquo;: inspired by <a href="http://www.inc.com/magazine/20040701/management.html">this post on Inc.com</a></li>
<li>&ldquo;Grundlagen der Sozialpsychologie II&rdquo; by Prof. Dr. Dieter Frey from LMU Munich on <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/de/itunes-u/grundlagen-der-sozialpsychologie/id422005471">iTunes U</a></li>
<li>&ldquo;Rechtsphilosophie&rdquo; by Prof. em. Dr. jur. Dr. jur. h.c. mult. Bernd Schünemann from LMU Munich on <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/de/itunes-u/lmu-rechtsphilosophie/id575246916">iTunes U</a></li>
</ol>


<p>Especially the various Coursera courses I take should provide material for about
one article a week, varying in length. Of course the blog will not in any way be
able to be a substite for actually taking the respective classes. But I hope I&rsquo;ll
be able to give you some insight into what it&rsquo;s all about and so you can decide
whether you want to sign up for one of its future sessions yourself.</p>

<h3>A note about comments</h3>

<p>As you may have noticed, there are no comment forms on the blog. One reason is
that the Disqus platform that&rsquo;s integrated with Octopress has been giving me lots
of headaches in the past.</p>

<p>But the other, much graver reason is that I&rsquo;m completely flabberghasted about the
law regarding comments on webpages in Germany. In a nutshell, it would require
very strict oversight and moderation on my part because if somebody &ndash; in an attempt
to troll, spam or for whatever reason &ndash; posts something that&rsquo;s illegal in Germany,
I would be personally held responsible.
And although I&rsquo;m doing this as a hobby, the fact that posts may occasionally
include software-development-related topics could lead a potential judge to
classify the blog as a &ldquo;commercial&rdquo; blog, leading to even more responsibilities.</p>

<p>But let&rsquo;s make it into an advantage: if you want to share your thoughts on a
certain subject, please <a href="mailto:blog@marcusilgner.com">send me a mail</a> and I will
respond or even make a follow-up post out of it.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m looking forward to getting feedback and hope I&rsquo;ll be able to inspire your own
thinking and learning.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I did that when Rails 4 was still in heavy development and JRuby not officially supported yet. It was fun, including writing some custom <a href="https://gist.github.com/milgner/4410238">PKCS#5 compatibility code</a>.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
