<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: imho | Extroverted Introspection]]></title>
  <link href="http://milgner.github.io/blog/categories/imho/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://milgner.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-09T13:35:59+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://milgner.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Marcus Ilgner]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[blog@marcusilgner.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thank you for thanking me]]></title>
    <link href="http://milgner.github.io/blog/2014/09/02/thank-you-for-thanking-me/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-02T20:54:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://milgner.github.io/blog/2014/09/02/thank-you-for-thanking-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the beginning of this year, I <a href="http://marcusilgner.com/blog/2014/01/24/friday-night-hack-logitech-k290-on-linux/">hacked together</a>
a <a href="https://github.com/milgner/k290-fnkeyctl">small utility</a> to reconfigure the
function keys on the Logitech K290 when on Linux.
Since then, I not only added a Arch Linux configuration but also received a couple
of pull requests to ensure compatibility with a number of different Linux
distributions and also improved support for udev, systemd and pm-utils.</p>

<p>But just as great as those pull requests are people writing to me and giving me
their thanks for writing this small utility.
Given how obscure a niche this tool is filling, there can&rsquo;t be that many users.
But despite that, I already received a couple of emails from happy people for
whom the tool proved useful.</p>

<p>So this post is to say &ldquo;thank you&rdquo; to all those who contributed or sent me one
of those mails. I got into software development to write good software that would
facilitate the life of its users or - while I was still in game development -
provide them some fun in their spare time.</p>

<p>Having said that, I can&rsquo;t describe how uplifting it is to me to find that I seem
to be successful in this mission. Receiving these emails goes a long way toward
restoring my faith in humanity <i class='emoji wink'></i>.
As a result, I want to encourage you to do the same every now and then: whenever
you find a piece of software to be useful - especially if it&rsquo;s written by a
single author or small team - take a couple of minutes to write its author(s) a
few lines to express your gratitude: they&rsquo;ll surely appreciate it.</p>

<p>Interestingly enough, there&rsquo;s a fairly current <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/issues/16731">&ldquo;issue&rdquo; on Github</a>,
thanking the Rails team for doing such a tremendous job in its development.
Feel free to chime in if you&rsquo;re using Rails or have been using it in the past!</p>

<p>So: thank you! Both for thanking me and for contributing to the world of open
source software!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
